Guide to the Clyde Roark Hoey Papers, 1943-1954 RL.00556
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Subjects ca. 1943-1954
  - Main Sequence
    - Army, 1947-1950, 2 folders (Box 137)
      Correspondence to and from individuals in the Army seeking changes of status, benefits, promotions, etc. A sample of surnames beginning with the letter C has been retained.
    - Army (continued), 1951-1952, 6 folders (Box 138)
    - Army Engineers (Box 139)
    - Asheville War Effort Industry,1951 (Box 139)
      Concerns efforts to build a guided missile plant
    - Atlantic and Pacific Tea Company, ca. 1949-1950, 2 folders (Box 139)
      North Carolina response to an anti-trust suit against A and P.
    - Atomic Energy, 1946-1947 (Box 139)
    - Billingeley Hospital, 1949-1951 (Box 139)
      Black hospital in Statesville, N. C.
    - Fort Bragg, 1953 (Box 139)
    - Fort Bragg--Cherry Point Railroad, expansion of facilities, etc., 2 folders (Box 139)
    - Bricker Amendment, 1953-1954, 4 folders (Box 140)
      Largely constituent response to this amendment concerning treaties and limiting of executive agreements.
    - Budget, ca,1947, 2 folders (Box 140)
    - Budget, 1947-1948 (Box 141)
    - Buggs Island, 1948-1951, 3 folders (Box 141)
      Various issues related to Buggs Island and Phillpot Dam, Includes items on archaeological excavation which would be affected by flooding; Roanoke River Flood Control Commission; requests for power transmission lines involving Duke Power Co., Carolina Power and Light, and the Southeastern Power Administration.
    - Butner Artillery Range,1949 (Box 141)
    - Cabarrus County Sesquicentennial,1949 (Box 141)
    - Cerebral Palsy (Box 141)
    - Civil Aeronautics Board, 1947-1951 (Box 141)
      Cases heard before the Board; material on airports in Winston-Salem, Lumberton, Greensboro, etc.
    - Chavez Election Contest,1953[?] (Box 142)
      Dispute over alleged fraud in New Mexico Senatorial election
    - Civil Rights and Black Affairs, 1945-1953 (Box 142)
      Material on specific bills, general attitudes, and black concerns; conflict over the seating of Bilbo (1946); Fair Employment Practices Commission and Truman civil rights proposals; anti-lynching, anti-poll tax legislation; Meharry College; letters to and from individuals supporting or opposing segregation; numerous other topics, See also North Carolina
    - College at Durham and Billingsley Hospital., 5 folders (Box 142)
    - Clark, Mark, 1951, 3 folders (Box 143)
      Proposed appointment of Gen. Clark as Ambassador to the Vatican.
    - Coal, 1949-1950 (Box 143)
      Coal shortage and strikes
    - Cable Dairy, 1949 (Box 143)
      Milk contracts with the Army
    - Communism, 1949-1950 (Box 143)
      Largely opinion mail on Communist Control Act, See also Socialist Trend
    - Communism - Freistadt Case, 1949, 2 folders (Box 143)
      Controversy concerning Atomic Energy Commission scholarship awarded to student at University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, later revealed to be a Communist sympathizer.
    - Copper,1947 (Box 144)
      Shortage; Patterson Bill (H. R. 2404)
    - Cotton, 1946-1951, 6 folders (Box 144)
      Stabilization of cotton market (1946); quotas, importation of Egyptian cotton, Japanese textiles competing with U. S. in the Belgian Congo ( 1947-1948 ); the Marshall Plan and loans (1948); cotton and peanut acreage bills (1950); ceiling price on raw cotton (1951); miscellaneous concerns of cotton industry.
    - Defense,1948, 1951 (Box 145)
    - Displaced Persons, ca. 1947-1950 (Box 145)
      Relaxation of immigration laws; Displaced Persons Commission; legislation
    - District Bills, 1946 (Box 145)
    - Edenton Air Base (Box 145)
    - Education ca. 1945-1947, 3 folders (Box 145)
      Mainly related to Federal aid to education
    - Education, 1948-1950, 4 folders (Box 146)
    - Education--Person County, N. C., 1951 (Box 146)
    - Expenditures in the Executive Committee, 1949 (Box 146)
    - Export Control, 1949 (Box 146)
    - Federal Communications Commission, 1944, 1948, 1950 (Box 146)
      Applications for radio station licenses; hearings; telephone and television applications, etc.
    - Federal Communications Commission, 1950-1954, 3 folders (Box 147)
    - Federal Employees Loyalty Fund--Investigation in Senate,1948 (Box 147)
      Correction of administrative loopholes and delays; printed preliminary report
    - Federal Housing Authority, 1947-1948 (Box 147)
    - Federal Power Commission, 1947-1953 (Box 147)
      Hearings and decisions; orders; natural gas applications; etc.
    - Federal Reserve Board--Regulation I, 1949-1950 (Box 147)
      Consumer credit for automobile purchases
    - Federal Reserve Board--Regulation W (Box 148)
    - Fertilizer 1947-1948 (Box 148)
      Fertilizer supplies; efforts to get increased nitrogen supply
    - Flight--50th Anniversary, 1953 (Box 148)
    - Greece, Aid to,1947 (Box 148)
    - Genocide Treaty, 1950 (Box 148)
    - Hawaii Statehood,1950, 1953-1954 (Box 148)
      Hoey's opposition to statehood because of racial differences and more support for civil rights measures in Congress
    - Health Insurance, 1949-1950, 2 folders (Box 148)
    - Health Insurance, 1951 (Box 149)
    - High Point Power Project, 1948, 1953 (Box 149)
    - Flood control and Yadkin River Dam; assistance through Federal Works Adm. (Box 149)
    - Hoover Commission, 2 folders (Box 149)
      See also Reorganization of Government
    - Hospital Projects 1950 (Box 149)
    - Housing, 1949- 1950 (Box 149)
      Includes material on low-cost public housing; National Cooperative Housing Act; Public Housing and Slum Clearance Bill; Real estate credit
    - Housing--Greensboro, N.C., 1951 (Box 150)
    - Housing--Home Loan Bank Board (Box 150)
    - Housing--Wilmington, 1948 (Box 150)
    - Immigration, 1949, 1953 (Box 150)
      Scant material on McCarran-Walter Act, See also Visas
    - India--Grain,1951 (Box 150)
    - Indian Affairs,1947, 1949-1950, 1954 (Box 150)
      Assorted items concerning American Indians, such as the selling of Indian land to the Methodist Church, the Eastern Band of Cherokee Indians, Cherokee Historical Association.
    - Indochina, 1954 (Box 150)
      Letters opposing involvement of troops.
    - Insurance--National Service, 1950 (Box 150)
    - Intergovernmental Relations Commission, 1953 (Box 150)
      Typescripts and material dealing with principles and historical development of the Federal government, etc.
    - Interstate Commerce Commission, 1949-1953 (Box 150)
    - Israel, Aid to,1951, Taft-Douglas Resolution (Box 151)
    - Japanese Internees, 1948 (Box 151)
    - Form letters (Box 151)
    - Justice Department, 1948 (some earlier dates) (Box 151)
      Memoranda concerning types of cases which F. B. I. clears with Department of Justice
    - Korea, 1950-1951, 4 folders (Box 151)
    - Korea, ca. 1951 (Box 152)
    - Labor, 1945-1948, 5 folders (Box 152)
      Various bills
    - Labor--Minimum wage, 1949, 3 folders (Box 153)
    - Labor, 1950 (Box 153)
    - Labor--Ralph Brimley, 1951 (Box 153)
      North Carolina educator appointed by War Department for special project, Labor organizations disapproved of Brimley and there was much public response
    - Labor--Railroad Strike, 1951 (Box 153)
    - Labor--Steel Mill Seizure, 1952, 3 folders (Box 154)
      Seizure of mills and action by Wage Stabilization Board. Letters by Hoey discuss the position of Southern Democrats on this issue.
    - Labor--Moody-Dingell Bill,1952, 3 folders (Box 154)
      S. 2504 designed to increase unemployment compensation benefits by Federal supplement to state unemployment.
    - Labor--Western Electric Co. N.C., 1952 (Box 155)
    - Labor--Taft-Hartley, 1953-1654 (Box 155)
    - Labor, 1953, 2 folders (Box 155)
      Includes surplus labor issue and Hoey's reaction to John F. Kennedy's proposal
    - Labor,1954 (Box 155)
    - Lanham Act,1945 (Box 155)
    - Camp Lejeune, 1951 (Box 156)
    - Library Bill, 1950 (Box 156)
    - MacArthur, Douglas, 2 folders (Box 156)
    - McCarthy, Joseph R. (Box 156)
    - Marshall Plan, 1948, 2 folders (Box 156)
    - Maxton-Laurinburg Air Base 1951 (Box 156)
      Plans to reactivate the base
    - Medical Bills, 1946-1947 (Box 157)
    - Military Service, Compulsory, 1946-1948, 5 folders (Box 157)
    - Military Service, Compulsory, 1948-1952, 5 folders (Box 158)
    - National Production Authority (Box 158)
    - Navy,1945 (Box 158)
      A sample of names beginning with the letter C has been retained for this correspondence concerning individual problems.
    - Navy, 1946-1951, 4 folders (Box 159)
    - New York Furniture Exchange, 1951 (Box 159)
    - North Carolina College at Durham, 1952 (Box 159)
      Mainly promotional photographs of the campus and dormitories
    - Oil Shortage, 1948-1950 (Box 159)
      Scant material on relations between independent and major oil companies investigated by a special committee on American small business. Also restrictions on importation of foreign oil.
    - Palestine, 1945-1947 (Box 159)
    - Palestine, ca. 1947 (Box 160)
    - Parks (National) and Roads, 1945-1954, 4 folders (Box 160)
      Blue Ridge Parkway and Smokey Mountains National Park expansion and development; Cherokee Reservation; appropriations for Currituck Beach Lighthouse and Wright Memorial; merger of Nantahala National Forest and Pisgah; television transmission station at Mt. Pisgah; and other topics.
    - Peanuts, ca. 1950-1951 (Box 160)
    - Poll Tax,1946 (Box 161)
    - Post Office ca. 1948, 1950 (Box 161)
      General postal concerns; postal legislation
    - Post Office--Delivery Cuts,1950, 3 folders (Box 161)
    - Post Office and Postal Concerns, 1950-1952, 2 folders (Box 161)
    - Post Office--Postal Employees, Ca.1953 (Box 162)
    - Post Office--Postal Rates, ca. 1953-1954 (Box 162)
    - Post Office, Wilkes Co., N. C. 1953 (Box 162)
    - Post Office and Postal Concerns,1952, 3 folders (Box 162)
    - Post Office and Postal Concerns, ca. 1953-1954 (Box 162)
    - Post Office and Postal Concerns, ca. 1953-1954, 4 folders (Box 163)
    - Post Office--Parcel Post Packages, ca. 1954 (Box 163)
    - Potatoes, 1950, 1952.Ceiling prices (Box 163)
    - Power Dam Appropriations, 1952 (Box 164)
    - Price Controls, 1948-1951, 5 folders (Box 164)
      Price control legislation and its effect on the textile industry; War Production Control Bill; Defense Production Act
    - Price Controls--Defense Production Act, 1951 (Box 165)
    - Price Controls, 1951, 2 folders (Box 165)
    - Prisoners, A-D, 3 folders (Box 165)
      Correspondence with prisoners or their families relating to pardons, parole, legal situations, etc.
    - Prisoners, E-Z, 4 folders (Box 166)
    - Prisoners--Martin, James T. (Box 166)
    - Prisoners--Sparrow, I. J. (Box 166)
    - Railroad Rates, 1948. Bulwinkle Bill (Box 167)
    - Railroad Retirement, 1946-1948, 5 folders (Box 167)
      Amendments to the Railroad Retirement and Unemployment Insurance Act
    - Railroad Retirement, 1948, 1951 (Box 168)
    - Raleigh-Durham Airport, 1948, 1951, 1953-1954 (Box 168)
      Reactivation of airport by Air Force; Weather Bureau installation
    - Reconstruction Finance Corporation, 1947-1951, 3 folders (Box 168)
    - Reconstruction Finance Corporation--Concrete and Asphalt Co., Inc., Charlotte, N. C., 1952 (Box 168)
    - Rent Control, 1948-1953 (Box 168)
    - Reorganization of Government, 1948-1949, 6 folders (Box 169)
      Various aspects of reorganization; proposals to place U. S. Employment Service under Dept, of Labor; implementation of Hoover Commission suggestions; exemption of various agencies, etc.
    - Reorganization of Government, 1949-1950, 7 folders (Box 170)
    - Reorganization of Government, 1952-1953, 2 folders (Box 171)
      Includes Internal Revenue Service and Health, Education, and Welfare provisions
    - Reserve Officers' Training Corps (Box 171)
      Efforts to establish R.O.T.C. units at schools such as Appalachian State, Atlantic Christian, Catawba, Elan and Gardner-Webb colleges
    - Reserve Troops (Box 171)
    - Rivers and Harbors, 1947-1949 (Box 171)
      Emergency bills, flood control, North Carolina projects, reports
    - Rivers and Harbors--Reddies River Dam, 1948 (Box 171)
    - Rivers and Harbors--Yadkin Valley Projects, ca. 1948-1951 (Box 171)
    - Rivers and Harbors--Wilmington, 1946-1952 (Box 172)
    - Rivers and Harbors, 1950-1954, 3 folders (Box 172)
      National Rivers and Harbors Congress (1950); North Carolina projects such as Cumberland River, Oregon Inlet, Neuse Valley development, Inland Waterway, dredging at Sealevel, etc.
    - Robinson-Patman Act,1954 (Box 172)
      Concerns retail sales
    - Roosevelt Highway, 1945 (Box 172)
    - Rotary Scholarships, 1952 (Box 173)
    - Rules (Senate), 1949. Civil rights filibuster (Box 173)
    - Rural Electrification Administration, 1946-1947, 1951.Bids, applications, and appropriations. (Box 173)
    - Savannah River Bomb Plant, 1951 (Box 173)
    - Seymour Johnson Airfield, 1951-1952 (Box 173)
    - Shrine Bowl Game, 1954.Tax exemption. (Box 173)
    - Social Security, 1949-1950, 2 folders (Box 173)
      Definitions, exemptions, and extensions of original act.
    - Social Security, 1950, 1953, 6 folders (Box 174)
    - Social Security, 1954 (Box 175)
    - Socialistic Trend, 1949 (Box 175)
      Chiefly form mimeograph letters on the Mundt Subversive Activities Bill. See also Communism
    - Spain, 1950 (Box 175)
      Loans; cotton, tobacco, and commodity supplies
    - Steel and Steel Mills. See Labor (Box 175)
    - Sugar, 1947, 1949,Quotas; importation from Cuba (Box 175)
    - Swiss Watch Quotas, 1945 (Box 175)
    - Tariffs--Imported China, 19501952 (Box 175)
    - Tariffs--Imported Rugs (China), 1950, 1952 (Box 175)
    - Tariffs--Torquay Conference (Box 175)
    - Tax, 1945-1947 (Box 175)
    - Tax measures of all kinds, 2 folders (Box 175)
    - Tax,1947, 3 folders (Box 176)
      Exemption for jewelry excise co-operatives Tax, 1948
    - Tax--Oleomargarine, 1948 (Box 176)
    - Tax--Beauty Shops, 1948 (Box 176)
    - Tax, 1949-1950, 6 folders (Box 177)
    - Tax, 1950-1951, 6 folders (Box 178)
    - Tax, 1951-1953, 6 folders (Box 179)
    - Tax, 1953-1954, 6 folders (Box 180)
    - Tax,1954, 6 folders (Box 181)
    - Tax, 1954, 6 folders (Box 182)
    - Tax, 1954, 3 folders (Box 183)
    - Tidelands Oil, 1949, 1952-1953, 3 folders (Box 183)
    - Tobacco, 1948-1951 (Box 184)
      Includes Dunn, West Jefferson, Rocky Mount, and Asheville markets and other topics.
    - Trade Agreements, 1945-1949, 1952-1953, 3 folders (Box 184)
      Reciprocal Trade Agreements Act (1945-49); Fair Trade Bill; extensions of Reciprocal Trade
    - Treaty, Italian, 1947 (Box 184)
    - Unemployment, 1945 (Box 184)
    - United Nations, 1949, 2 folders (Box 184)
      Amending U. N. charter; inspection teams.
    - Vatican,1950 (Box 185)
      Appointment of Ambassador. See also Clark, Mark.
    - Veterans, Ca - Cz, 4 folders (Box 185)
      C sample of individual cases. Arranged alphabetically by veteran's name.
    - Veterans Legislation--Terminal Leave Pay, 1946-1947, 2 folders (Box 185)
    - Veterans Legislation-Spanish-American War, 1947 (Box 186)
    - Veterans Legislation, 1948-1949 (Box 186)
      Farm training, veterans bonus, other programs
    - Veterans Legislation, ca. 1949-1953, 2 folders (Box 186)
      Loans, various bills
    - Veterans--Southeastern Peoples' College, Charlotte, N. C., 1950-1951 (Box 186)
    - Veterans--Winston-Salem Barbers College (N. C.) 1951 (Box 186)
    - Visas, A - Ka, 6 folders (Box 187)
      Correspondence concerning visas, passports, and travel or immigration procedures for individuals.
    - Visas, Ke - P, 5 folders (Box 188)
    - Visas, Q - Z, 4 folders (Box 189)
    - War Assets Administration, 1948 (Box 189)
      Hospital and recreational equipment; Butner Hospital.
    - West Point--Cadet Investigation, 1951 (Box 189)
      Cheating scandal.
  - Miscellaneous Legislation
    - Miscellaneous Legislation,1948 (Box 190)
    - Miscellaneous Legislation, 1948-1949 (Box 191)
    - Miscellaneous Legislation,1949 (Box 192-194)
    - Miscellaneous Legislation, 1949-1950 (Box 195)
    - Miscellaneous Legislation,1950 (Box 196-197)
    - Miscellaneous Legislation,1951 (Box 198-200)
    - Miscellaneous Legislation,1952 (Box 201-205)
    - Miscellaneous Legislation, 1952-1953 (Box 206)
    - Miscellaneous Legislation,1953 (Box 207-208)
    - Miscellaneous Legislation,1954 (Box 209-210)
  - Statements and Speeches
    - ca. 1945-1946 (Box 211)
      Includes the following speeches:
      - Founders' Day Meeting Appalachian State Teachers College Boone, N. C., May 8, 1945.Tribute to President B. Bo Dougherty (Box 211)
      - Chamber of Commerce Banquet Shelby, N. C., Mar. 30, 1945 (Box 211)
      - Address, National Broadcasting Company, May 11, 1945 (Box 211)
      - Graduating Class, Bowman-Gray School of Medicine Winston-Salem, N. C., June 17, 1945 (Box 211)
      - International Relations Institute, Woman's College, University of North Carolina, June 11, 1945 (Box 211)
      - Statement on appointment of Henry Wallace as Secretary of Commerce (Box 211)
      - Foreign Treaties (Box 211)
      - Electric Power Industry in N. C. (Box 211)
      - Universal Military Training Virginia Annual Conference (Education) Oct. 17, 1945 (Box 211)
      - Veterans and Peace (Box 211)
      - Board of Trade and Merchants of Brevard, Aug. 16, 1945 (Box 211)
      - Textile Industry Federal Aid to Education (Box 211)
      - Life Insurance Association of America, New York City, Dec. 13, 1946 (Box 211)
      - On the Death of Josiah W. Bailey, 1946 (Box 211)
      - State Convention of Young Democrats; Asheville, Oct. 12, 1946 (Box 211)
      - 4-H Conference, Aug. 13, 1946 (Box 211)
      - Annual Garden Display of Ecusta Paper Co., Pisgah Forest, Sept. 6, 1946 (Box 211)
      - Statement on School Bond Issue (Box 211)
      - Coal Strike (Box 211)
      - Equal Rights Amendment (Box 211)
      - Does Congress Listen to Women's Clubs? Kiwanis Club, Charlotte, N. C., Aug. 29, 1946 (Box 211)
      - Dedication of soldier's marker, Bladen Co. (Box 211)
      - Chamber of Commerce Banquet, N. C. April 26, 1946 (Box 211)
      - North Carolina State Federation of Women's Clubs, Greensboro, May 30, 1946 (Box 211)
      - Labor issues, 1946-1947 (Box 211)
    - ca, 1947-1949 (Box 211)
      - Tax Reduction Bill, 1947 (Box 211)
      - Commencement, Greensboro College, June 2, 1947 (Box 211)
      - Labor Legislation (Box 211)
      - Regional Meeting, Lions Club, Statesville, Sept, 16, 1947 (Box 211)
      - N. C. Food Dealers Association, Asheville, N. C., Sept, 9, 1947 (Box 211)
      - Bulwinkle Bill (1948) (Box 211)
      - State Issues, 1948 (Box 211)
      - Marshall Plan, 1948 (Box 211)
      - Labor Unions, 1948 (Box 211)
      - Reorganization of Government,1948 (Box 211)
      - Southern Democrats, 1948 (Box 211)
      - Jefferson-Jackson Day Dinner of Virginia Democrats, Feb. 19, 1948 (Box 211)
      - Anti-Lynch Law, 1948 (Box 211)
      - Roads and Trails in National Parks, 1948 (Box 211)
      - Incidents Showing Relationship of the Races in N. C. ca. 1948 (Box 211)
      - Crop Acreage Allotments (Box 211)
      - Greeting on the occasion of the Jewish New Year (Box 211)
      - State Building and Loan League, Annual Convention, Blowing Rock, June 13, 1949 (Box 211)
      - Releases from Senate Investigations Subcommittee (Hoey as Chairman),1949 (Box 211)
      - National Civitan Convention (Box 211)
      - Dedication of Student Union Memorial Building to O. Max Gardner, Gardner-Webb College, April 7, 1949 (Box 211)
      - State Convention, United Daughters of the Confederacy, Oct. 11, 1949 (Box 211)
      - North Atlantic Treaty (Box 211)
      - Amending Rule and Civil Rights (Box 211)
    - ca. 1950-1952
      - 1950
        - Alaska data (Box 211)
        - on Faith of our Fathers by Paul Green (Box 211)
        - Genocide Treaty (Box 211)
        - Displaced Persons (Box 211)
        - World Federation Resolution (Box 211)
        - Federal Power Commission and Roanoke Rapids Dam (Box 211)
        - Dedication, Montgomery Co. Memorial Hospital, Troy, N. C., Mar, 5, 1950 (Box 211)
        - National Compulsory Health Laws (Box 211)
        - Farming data (Box 211)
        - Korea (Box 211)
        - Fair Employment Practices Commission (Box 211)
      - 1951
        - Dismissal of Dr. Ralph Brimley by the Army under pressure from A. F. of L. (Box 211)
        - Ceiling on Raw Cotton (Box 211)
        - MacArthur (Box 211)
        - Taft on Isolationism (Box 211)
        - Defense Production Act (Box 211)
      - 1952
        - Steel Mill Seizure (Box 211)
        - Richard Russell and the Democratic Convention (Box 211)
        - Reorganization of Government (Box 211)
      - ca. 1953-1954and undated
        - 1953
          - Children of the Confederacy State Convention, Chapel Hill, Aug. 27 (Box 211)
          - Memorial Service for Willis Smith, July 1 (Box 211)
          - Memorandum on New Mexico Senatorial Contest (See, Chavez) (Box 211)
          - Yale Political Union, New Haven, Jan. 15 (Box 211)
          - Farm Situation (Box 211)
          - Agricultural Program (Box 211)
          - Rouss Banquet, Winchester, Va, Feb. 11 (Box 211)
          - State Baptist Pastors' Conference, Greensboro, Nov. 9 (Box 211)
          - Response to John F. Kennedy's request to classify New England as surplus labor area (Box 211)
        - 1954
          - Bricker Amendment (Box 211)
          - Farm situation (Box 211)
        - Undated statements and speeches (Box 211)
          Several major categories:
          --topics of national concern (cigarette taxes, Southeastern Power Administration appropriations, U. N. Charter amendments, Housing Bill, Rent Control, communists in the State Dept., British loans, etc.)
          --general topics (Importance of Congress, the need for unity, North Carolina young people, temperance, the obligation to vote
          --reviews of books
          --announcements or commemoration of deaths of colleagues
          --religious reflections (the Bible, Sunday School, Faith, etc.)
  - Miscellany
    - Campaign data, 1944 (Box 211)
    - Convention Memorabilia, 1952 (Box 211)